Today,
اليوم،
a baffled lady observed
لاحظت سيدة مرتبكة
the shell where my soul dwells
الصدفة حيث تسكن روحي
And announced that I'm
وأعلنت أنني
"articulate"
"فصيحة."
Which means that when it comes
مما يعني أنه عندما يتعلق الأمر
to enunciation and diction
بالنطق والإلقاء
I don't even think of it
لا ألقي لها بالا حتى
‘Cause I’m "articulate"
لأنني "فصيحة".
So when my professor asks a question
لذا حينما يسأل أستاذي سؤالا
And my answer is tainted with a connotation
ويكون جوابي ذا صبغة ضمنية
of urbanized suggestion
لاقتراح حضاري،
There’s no misdirected intention
فليست هناك نية مضللة
Pay attention
انتبه!
‘Cause I’m “articulate”
لأنني " فصيحة."
So when my father asks, “Wha’ kinda ting is dis?”
لذلك حين يسأل أبي، "ما هذا الشيء؟"
My “articulate” answer never goes amiss
لا يخطىء جوابي "المبين" أبدا.
I say “father, this is the impending problem at hand”
فأقول: "أبي، لدينا مشكل وشيك الحدوث."
And when I’m on the block
وحين أكون في الحي
I switch it up just because I can
فإنني أغير لغتي لأنه بإمكاني فعل ذلك.
So when my boy says, “What’s good with you son?”
وحين يقول ابني "ما الأمر الحسن الذي يحدث معك يا بني؟"
I just say, “I jus’ fall out wit dem people but I done!”
أقول
And sometimes in class
وأحيانا في الفصل
I might pause the intellectual sounding flow to ask
ربما أوقف تدفق سبر أفكاري لأسأل،
“Yo! Why dese books neva be about my peoples”
أنتم! لم لم تكن تلك الكتب قط عن أقوامي؟"
Yes, I have decided to treat
أجل، لقد قررت أن أتعامل
all three of my languages as equals
مع اللغات الثلاث بالتساوي
Because I’m “articulate”
لأنني "فصيحة".
But who controls articulation?
لكن من يتحكم في الفصاحة؟
Because the English language is a multifaceted oration
لأن اللغة الإنجليزية خطاب متعدد الأوجه.
Subject to indefinite transformation
وهي موضع لتغيرات غير محدودة.
Now you may think that it is ignorant to speak broken English
الآن قد تعتقدون أنه من الجهل التحدث بإنجليزية غير سليمة.
But I’m here to tell you that even “articulate” Americans
لكنني هنا لأقول لكم أن الأمريكيين "الفصيحين"
sound foolish to the British
يبدون كالحمقى بالنسبة للبريطانيين.
So when my Professor comes on the block and says, “Hello”
لذا فحين يأتي أستاذي إلى القسم ويقول "مرحبا"،
I stop him and say “Noooo …
أوقفه قائلة: لا...
You’re being inarticulate …
فأنت غير فصيح.
the proper way is to say ‘what’s good’”
الصحيح أن تقول " ما الجيد عندك".
Now you may think that’s too hood, that’s not cool
الآن قد تعتقدون أن هذا سوقي جدا، هذا غير رائع.
But I’m here to tell you that even our language has rules
لكنني هنا لأقول لكم أن للغتنا أيضا قواعد.
So when Mommy mocks me and says
لذا فحين تسخر أمي مني قائلة:
“ya’ll-be-madd-going-to-the-store”
"ستذهبون جميعكم وبإفراط إلى المتجر."
I say “Mommy, no, that sentence is not following the law
أجيبها: "أمي، لا، هذه جملة لا تتبع القوانين؛
Never does the word "madd" go before a present participle
فكلمة "بإفراط" لا تسبق أبدا "النعت الحالي،
That’s simply the principle of this English”
لأن هذا هو مبدأ اللغة الإنجليزية هذه"
If I had the vocal capacity I would
لو كانت لي قدرة صوتية،
sing this from every mountaintop,
لكنت غنيت هذا من أعلى قمة أي جبل،
From every suburbia, and every hood
من كل الضواحي، من كل حي،
‘Cause the only God of language is the one recorded in the Genesis
لأن إله هذه اللغة الوحيد هو ذاك الذي سجل نشأة
Of this world saying “it is good"
هذا العالم القائل "أنه بخير".
So I may not always come before you
لذا فقد لا أقف أمامكم دائما
with excellency of speech
بتميز في الخطاب،
But do not judge me by my language and assume
لكن لا تحكموا علي بلغتي وتفترضوا
That I’m too ignorant to teach
أنني جاهلة ولا يمكن أن أدرس،
‘Cause I speak three tongues
لأنني أتكلم 3 لغات.
One for each:
واحدة لكل من:
Home, school and friends
البيت والمدرسة والأصدقاء.
I’m a tri-lingual orator
أنا متحدثة ذات ثلاثة ألسن.
Sometimes I’m consistent with my language now
أحيانا أكون متناغمة مع لغتي الحالية؛
Then switch it up so I don’t bore later
بعدها أغيرها لكي لا أُشعر الآخر بالملل لاحقا.
Sometimes I fight back two tongues
أحيانا أكبح لغتين
While I use the other one in the classroom
حين أستعمل الأخرى داخل القسم.
And when I mistakenly mix them up
لكن حين أمزجها كلها خطأ
I feel crazy like … I’m cooking in the bathroom
أشعر بالجنون وكأنني أطبخ في الحمام.
I know that I had to borrow your language
أعلم أنه كان علي أن أستعير لغتكم،
because mines was stolen
لأن لغاتي سُرِقت.
But you can’t expect me to speak your history wholly
لكن لا تتوقعوا مني أن أتحدث عن تاريخكم بالكلية،
while mines is broken
بينما تواريخي كلها واهنة.
These words are spoken
هذه كلمات منطوقة
By someone who is simply fed up with
من طرف شخص ضاق ذرعا
the Eurocentric ideals of this season
بالمثل العليا الأوروبية لعصرنا.
And the reason I speak a composite version of your language
والسبب في أنني أتحدث نسخة مركبة من لغتكم،
Is because mines was raped away along with my history
هو أن لغاتي تم اغتصابها على طول تاريخي.
I speak broken English so the profusing gashes can remind us
أتحدث لغة غيرسليمة لكي تذكرنا هذه الجروح النازفة
That our current state is not a mystery
أن وضعنا الراهن ليس غامضا.
I’m so tired of the negative images that are driving my people mad
لقد سئمت من الصور السلبية التي تجعل الناس قلقين.
So unless you’ve seen it rob a bank stop calling my hair bad
ما لم تروه يسرق مصرفا، توقفوا عن وصف شعري بالسيء.
I’m so sick of this nonsensical racial disparity
لقد سئمت من ذلك التفاوت العنصري التافه.
So don’t call it good unless your hair is known
لذلك لا تنعتوه بالجيد حتى يكون شعركم معروفا
for donating to charity
بتقديم التبرعات.
As much as has been raped away from our people
بقدر ما تم سلبه من مجموعاتنا،
How can you expect me to treat their imprint on your language
كيف لكم أن تتوقعوا مني أن أتعامل مع بصمتهم للغتكم
As anything less than equal
بأقل من التساوي.
Let there be no confusion
فلنقطع الالتباس،
Let there be no hesitation
فلنقطع التردد.
This is not a promotion of ignorance
ليست هذه دعوة للجهل،
This is a linguistic celebration
هذا احتفال لغوي.
That’s why I put "tri-lingual" on my last job application
لهذا وضعت " ثلاثية الألسن" في آخر طلب وظيفة لي.
I can help to diversify your consumer market
يمكن أن أساعدكم في تنويع سوق مستهلكيهم،
is all I wanted them to know
كل ما أردتهم أن يعرفوا.
And when they call me for the interview
وحين يتصلون بي من أجل مقابلة العمل،
I’ll be more than happy to show that
سأكون سعيدة جدا لأريهم
I can say:
أنني أستطيع أن أقول:
“What’s good”
"ما الجيد؟"
“Whatagwan”
"ما الذي يجري"
And of course …“Hello”
وبطبيعة الحال..."مرحبا"
Because I’m “articulate”
لأنني" فصيحة".
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)